我的挚友
"My dear friend Gaius,
盖乌斯
我们之间怎么会出现
how are we come
这么荒谬的情况呢？
to this absurd position?
为了和平与公道
In the interests of peace and equity,
我接受 元老院和罗马的人民
I accept--"  The Senate and People of Rome
授权我接受
have authorized me to accept.
元老院和罗马的人民
"...the Senate and People of Rome
已经授权我接受休战…
have authorized me to accept a truce--"
不，不能说休战，那会暗示
No, not truce. That would imply
他是君主而不是罪人
that he is a sovereign rather than a criminal entity.
对啊
Quite right. A criminal.
罪人
已经授权我接受
"...have authorized me to accept
停止敌对状态的建议
a cessation of hostilities...
在你上一封信所提出的条件之下
on the terms offered in your last letter.
我会等待你的回复
I await your answer."
够好了吧  够好了？
Good enough.  Good enough?
这种卑鄙的羞辱也能说好吗？
This abject humiliation is good enough?
我们不能称为人，我们简直就是虫子
We are not men. We are worms.
虫子太难听了
Worms is harsh.
虫子可没有我们跑得快
Worms cannot run away as speedily as we do.
恺撒甚至还没有离开罗马
Caesar has not even left Rome,
老天才知道为什么
Gods know why not,
可是他的军团追击我们
yet his legions chase us
毫不费力的从这个城镇追到那个城镇
from town to town with great ease.
与其说是虫子不如说我们是一群绵羊
We're more like sheep than worms.
要是我们还有税收，要是我们还有钱供养军队
If our levies had not failed, if we had money to pay troops--
是啊，他们有，我们却没有
Yes, but they have and we don't.
让我们坚守现在仅存的硕果吧，庞贝，
Let us cleave to the matter at hand. Pompey, you must give
你应该找个时间单独和他会晤
some notion of when you will agree to meet him in person.
不可能
Never.  There is no reason for them to meet.
他们没有理由会晤
纷争是在恺撒和元老院之间
The dispute is between Caesar and the Senate.
这才是正式的途径
It is the proper form.  I'll not meet the man.
我不会去见他的，决不，
Never. Like a son, he was to me.
他对我来说就像是我的儿子
他像你什么毫不重要
What he was like to you is immaterial.
出于朱庇特神的怜悯
It is only by Jupiter's mercy
他才没有把我们的头串在长矛上面
that he has not already put our heads on pikes.
怜悯？
Mercy? Jupiter has no mercy for cowards.
朱庇特神可不会怜悯懦夫
你说话小心点  你要讨论接受或者反对投降？
Cato, be careful.  You'll accept abject surrender--
这不是投降！
This is not surrender!
庞贝·马格纳斯不会投降
Pompey Magnus does not surrender.
我需要时间
I need time.
休战会为我们争取那些时间
A truce gains us that time.
法拉斯·霍塔送来三罐琥珀
verrus Horta sends three jars of amber
还告诉我们他已经脱离了庞贝的阵营
and informs us he has left the standard of Pompey.
并且请求在您的庇护下继续生活
He entrusts his living to your abundant mercy.
霍塔？ 就是那个白白的皮肤，红红的头发…
Horta?  Pederast, waxy skin, red hair,
住在塔斯库勒姆，我认识他，是个可怜虫
estates in Tusculum.  I have him, the wretch.
给他送去一小袋钱
Send a small bag of money with a fulsome letter
让他当个财务官什么的好了
and make him a Quaestor or something.
要是对每个遗弃庞贝的人都给这种恩惠的话
Show such mercy to every man that deserts Pompey,
你会变成穷光蛋的，这种人每天都来上好几打
you will pauperize yourself. There's dozens of them coming every day.
善用恩惠能给你换来1万兵力
Judicious use of mercy is worth 10,000 men.
要是花光我口袋里面的钱能给我买个王位的话，那也值得
And if my last coin buys me a throne, it's a fair price.
王位？ 这是诗的破格，还能是什么呢？
A throne?  Poetic license. What else?
阿提娅邀请您用晚餐
Atia invites you to dinner tonight.
又来了？老天
Again? Bona Dea.
今天晚上不行  我得给个什么理由呢？
Not tonight in any case.  What excuse shall I give?
什么都不用解释
None.  This is the second time
这可是您第二次拒绝她的邀请了
you have refused an invitation from her.
我不需要向阿提娅说明什么
I need not account for myself to Atia.
如您所说，也许这不是一个聪明的选择，不过的确很勇敢
As you say. Not a sapient choice, perhaps; but brave, sure.
人们说奴隶谈勇敢就如鱼想飞翔一样不切实际
They say slaves talk of bravery as fish talk of flying.
他们这么说吗？真够幽默的
They say that, do they? How very witty of them.
为了寻求正义与和平
"Seeking only justice and peace
避免无谓的流血事件在罗马发生
and to avoid the unnecessary shedding of Roman blood,
盖乌斯·朱利叶斯·恺撒公开恳求
Gaius Julius Caesar has publicly implored
背叛者庞贝·马格纳斯
the renegade Gnaius Pompey Magnus
接受休战并且放下武器
to accept truce and lay down his arms."
你们在干什么？
What are you doing?
这个挺有意思的，就像是艺术
It's rather fun, and there's quite an art to it.
这个古怪的孩子
Strange boy.
我刚刚听到奇怪事情
I have just heard a very strange tale
从厨房工人那里听来关于你的
about you from the kitchen staff.
我真是很想知道
For what possible reason I wonder,
你和恺撒偷偷躲在厨房里面干什么
would you and Caesar be skulking about in a cupboard?
什么？
What? We were- it was nothing.
我们…没什么
没什么？听起来不像嘛
Nothing? It doesn't sound like nothing.
你在勾引他？你个狡猾的小狐狸
You seduced him, you sly little fox.
我没有
I did not.  I am not clear it is decent,
我不知道这正不正当
him being your great uncle, but who's to say what's
他可是你的舅公哦，谁能说呢？
decent in times like these? In any case, well done.
这年头，什么东西才是正当？
不管怎么样，干得好
让我们看看赛维莉亚和你这个小男孩竞争
Let's see Servilia compete with a soft young boy like you.
我们真是能干啊
What power we shall wield.  You have it wrong.
你想错了
A good lover is a discreet lover.
好的情人一定是个谨慎的情人
他那时候不舒服，我只不过在照料他，仅此而已
He was taken ill. I was helping him to recover, that's all.
当然是了，我的小可爱，
Of course he was, my dove. Now in the future you must not appear too eager.
不过日后你不能表现得太饥渴
男人们就是喜欢难弄到手的东西
A man likes it if you play hard to get.
你不要烦他了，妈妈
Why don't you leave him alone, mother?  Now, I have invited
我已经邀请了恺撒和马克·安东尼过来吃晚餐
Caesar and Mark Antony for dinner tonight.
我们会保证你看起来
We'll be sure you look especially handsome--
特别帅气  我不是他的情人！
I am not his lover!
别对我撒谎
Do not lie to me.
你知道你撒谎我会看出来的  我没有
You know I detest it.  I am not lying.
他有时候会很痛苦，非常痛苦
He has an affliction. A terrible affliction.
痛苦？什么痛苦？谁弄的？
Affliction? What affliction? By whom?
我…我不会再说了，我立过誓
I- I will speak no more of it. I swore an oath.
去他的誓言，我可是你妈妈，告诉我
Oath be damned! I am your mother. Tell me.
原谅我，我不能说
Excuse me. I will not.
真是让人失望
Well, that's very disappointing.
恺撒派人来说他不会来赴宴了
Caesar sends to say he cannot come this evening.
无所谓了
No matter.
为什么不来？
Why not?  He doesn't say.
他没说
泰特斯·波罗又睡在楼梯上了
Titus Pullo is sleeping on the stairs again.
他就不能去别的地方？ 他不会在罗马呆太长时间的
Has he nowhere else to go?  He won't be in Rome much longer.
告诉我，那个年轻人什么时候回来？你的丈夫
Tell me, when is the youth returning? Your husband.
克理图  克理图，
Crito.  When does he return from his droving?
他什么时候能卖完牲口回来？
十一月，为什么？ 我今天要把奴隶卖了
November. Why?  I'm selling my slaves today.
那就会有钱给你买嫁妆了
There'll be money enough spare for your dowry.
他一回来，你和卢休斯就可以到他那里
So when Crito comes home, you and Lucius can go to him
好好的过你们小日子
and start your married life proper.  Thank you, Father!
谢谢你，爸爸 谢谢，
Thank you.  We'll be sorry to see you go.
我们看到你要走真是不舍得
November? It's so soon.
十一月？太快了
They have to go at some time.  Of course, of course,
-他们没过一段时间就得走了
-是的，没错 可是十一月  -我知道这很难，
but November.  It's hard, but it has to be done.
但是早晚总得这么做
They'll be so far away. You know how these drovers live.
他们要去很远，你知道这种牲畜贩子怎么生活
但是妈妈，我要去，我要和我的丈夫在一起
But Mama, I want to go. I want to be with my husband.
我知道，我知道，当然了
I know. I know. Of course.
你必须得走
You must go.
就是太难了
It's just hard.
早上好
Morning.
麻烦讨口水喝？
Trouble you for some water?
坐吧
Sit down.
你应该呆在军营里
You should be in camp.  Nothing to do there.
在那里无所事事 -真是无聊
It's boring.  Take some bread.
吃点面包
I'll not, thanks.
不用了，谢谢
我觉得不是很舒服
I'm not feeling too well.
你喝太多了
You're drinking too much.
没有，不是那样的
No, it's not that.
我吃了腐烂的牡蛎
I ate some depraved oysters.
你的女人呢？
Where's your girl?  Girl?
女人？
糟了！
Cac!
我知道就在这里面，我知道的
I know it's one of these. I know it!
别担心了
Stop worrying.
就算找不到了，你还可以在找另一个嘛
Even if we can't find her, you can get another.
我不要另一个
I don't want another. I want Eirene.
我要爱琳妮
You'll be off south after Pompey before long.
你不用多久就得南征去打庞贝了
不可能带着她上路的
You can't take her soldiering.
可能我就不归队了
Maybe I won't go back to camp.
反正我的服役时间也差不多了
My time is nearly done anyway.
离开第13军团？为什么？
Leave the 13th? Why?
你不就走了吗？ 你又不是我
You did.  You are not me.
你没有和平的天分
You have no talent for peace.
我不能扔下她不管
I can't just leave her.
你就只会用老二思考
You think with your penis.  It's not like that.
不是那样的
I've not touched her.  Then what purpose does she serve?
我碰都没碰过她  那你要她干嘛？
我喜欢看着她，能让我感到平静
I just like to look at her. Makes me calm.
她在那里呢
Here she is.
感谢你，阿波罗神
Thank you, Apollo.
那个女孩儿是他的
The girl is his.
别找麻烦，欠债还钱
No trouble. Pay what's owed,
女孩儿你就可以带走了  欠债？
and the girl is all yours.  What's owed?
给我吃了那些垃圾你该给我钱才对
You should be paying me to drink the pond filth you serve here.
波罗！
Pullo!
多少钱？
How much?
我一有钱就马上还你
I'll pay you back soon as I can.
好吧，
Do that.
不过你要拿她怎么办？
So what will you do with her?
我不要她呆在这里
I don't want her.  Say again?
再说一次？
I don't want her. It's nice of you to think of it--
我不要她，你们想得倒是好…
你不是要个奴隶吗？一直都想要的
But you want a slave. You keep asking for one,
这就给你带了一个来，波罗没法安置她，我们又不用花钱
and here she is. Pullo can't keep her, and it costs us nothing.
我就不能要一个你的高卢奴隶？
Can't I have one of your Gaulish slaves?
我跟你说过，我的高卢奴隶还没驯化呢
I've told you, my Gauls are unseasoned.
擦完地板就会把你的喉咙给割了
Cut your throat as soon as sweep your floor.
这个受过训练，又干净又听话
This one's trained up nice and docile.
她有什么不好的？
What is wrong with her?
她的眼神很奇怪
She has strange eyes.  You drive me insane!
你快让我疯了
女孩儿留下来
The girl stays.
冷静点，宝贝，冷静点
Keep calm, sweetie. Keep calm.
我怎么能冷静，波罗
How can I be calm when Pullo's put that little witch to spy on me?
把那个小贱人留下来监视我
他知道了，莉莎，他知道了
He knows, Rissa, he knows.
就他那样的傻大个儿？
Big simple brute like that?
就算他怀疑什么事情
If he even suspected anything,
他肯定会马上告诉乌瑞纳斯的，不是吗？
he'd go straight to vorenus and tell him, wouldn't he?
你真的这么想？
Course he would.  You really think?
他什么都不知道  真的？
He doesn't know nothing.  Really?
当然了。他看到伊万达在你的房子里
Sure of it. So he saw Evander round your house.
那又怎么样？他是你的家人，当然可以进来
So what? He's family. He's allowed.
那倒是  你不用担心的
That's true.  You're getting worried over nothing.
上帝，希望如此吧
Gods, let it be so.
那个可怜虫把你要的都给你了
Poor sad wretch gives everything you asked for.
元老院认可你的地位
The Senate will ratify your status,
你得到胜利，成为执政官
you get your triumph, stand for consul,
而庞贝就撤退到西班牙
and Pompey shall withdraw to Spain.
要是我们要求的话估计他还会答应亲波斯卡的小鸡鸡呢
He'll suck Posca's cock if asked nicely.
这也太慷慨了吧
Too generous by far. I never thought for an instant
我从未想过要接受这样的条款
Pompey would accept such terms.  You think it's a stratagem?
你认为这是他的诡计？
I doubt it.
我怀疑
他和他的军队都已经被困了
He and what few forces he has are trapped.
他已经弱下来了，而且每天都在败落
He's weak and growing weaker every day.
我们随时都可以让他完蛋
We might crush him at will.
不过既然他答应了休战
But now that he has offered truce,
如果我再去攻打他，那我就显得是个暴君了
I will look like the worst kind of tyrant if I attack him.
波斯卡认为我应该接受休战
Posca here thinks I should accept the truce.
缔造和平  那能够换来什么？
Make peace.  In exchange for what?
和平本身就是回报
Peace is it's own reward.  Snivelry.
妇人之仁
The ram has touched the wall. No mercy.
撞锤已经贴在城墙外面了，不能仁慈
庞贝身边没有军队，但是有元老院
Pompey has no great army, but he has the Senate with him.
他带有合法性
He has legitimacy.  In Rome they are the Senate.
他们在罗马才是元老院
走出了城墙他们不过是300个没有用的老头儿
Beyond the walls they are just 300 old men.
你说的有道理，安东尼，但是别人会认同波斯卡的看法，
As you say, Antony, but others will agree with Posca.
不过他们已经公开向我投降了
They have made this shameful surrender public.
整个意大利都会知道
It will be read all over ltaly.
如果我不是暴君
If I am not a tyrant,
如果我要的只是合法性
if I merely seek legitimacy,
为什么不能接受他们的条款呢？
why would I not accept such favorable terms?
他拒绝与我们会晤
He refuses to meet us...
单独的会晤？
in person?
很好，这个简单
very good. Simple.
民众会明白这么一个理由
Hoi polloi can understand a reason like that.
他拒绝见我
He refuses to meet me face to face.
拒绝面对面地见我
Man to man.
拒绝会晤
He refuses to meet me.
对，就是这个了
Right, that's it.
决不休战，
No truce. Let's be after them.
我们这就追他
Patience.
耐心点
他跑不了的
He's well caught.
等时机成熟了我们再出发
We'll leave when the time is right.
什么时候？
When?
时机成熟之时
When the time is right.
我们早就应该离开罗马了
But we should have left Rome long ago.
苹果熟了早该摘了
The apple is ripe for the plucking,
而我们却呆坐着什么都不干？
and we just sit here doing nothing?
庞贝不是苹果
Pompey is not an apple
我也不是农夫
and I am not a farmer.
传守卫
Call for my guard.
百夫长卢休斯·乌瑞纳斯
First Spear Centurion Lucius Vorenus.
等你回来等了好久
I have been looking for your return.
我退役了，公民
I'm no longer in the army, citizen.
我来把存货给卖了
I've come to sell my stock.
啊，嗯…
Ah,well...
脱水腹泻，我无能为力
Black blood flux. Nothing to be done.
腹泻？
Flux?  I kept 'em here despite the stink
虽然臭不可当，但是我可是还把他们留着
so you'd know I'd done you nothing dodgy.
所以我没有耍什么花招
也不是谁的错
Nobody to blame.
还好你还剩下一个
Fortune left you one at least.
就是那个幸运的孩子
Auspicious boy that is.  How much will he fetch?
那能换多少钱？
哦，一大笔钱
Oh, a respectable price.
足够把喂养费还了还有剩下的
More than enough to pay the feed bill.
喂养费？
Feed bill?  They didn't starve to death.
他们可没有饿死
快走！
Move!
什么都没了？
Nothing?  Not nothing. The boy will fetch
不是一无所有，
a good price when he's healthy.  What's that?
这小孩子健康起来后能卖个好价钱
Your father brought him back from Gaul. What will we do till then?
那是什么？  你爸爸把他从高卢带回来的，
在那之前我们能怎么样？
To keep?
养着他？  等他有点血色我们就把他卖了
We're selling him as soon as he gets some color.
那卖了之后呢？
What will we do after that?  What's his name?
他叫什么名字？ 没有名字
He hasn't got one!
我把他叫做卢比奥，那是我死去的鸽子的名字
We'll call him Rubio after my pigeon that died.
我们什么都没了
We've nothing saved.
别担心，我们会想到有的
Don't worry. I will think of something.
又是这样
And again.
又输了
This is a rout.
我要不要仁慈点呢？
Shall I be merciful?
还是不要
I think not.
你该怎么还我的债呢？
How will you pay your debt?
我的就是你的
All that I have is already yours.
还能给你什么呢？
What else can I give you?
别再离开我
Don't leave me again.
我从没有离开过你
I never left you.
人们都无聊疯了
The men are going mad from boredom.
今天我不得不割下一个骁勇的战士的双手因为他
Just today I had to cut the hands off a perfectly good Legionary
杀害了一个平民
for murdering a civilian.
接着 又得听一个不知道哪里来的自由民
Then I had to listen to a jumped up freedman
胡说八道了半天
raving for hours
说有个百夫长在勾引他的女儿
about one of my centurions seducing his daughters.
听起来无聊死了
It all sounds very tedious.  It is your uncle's fault.
都是你舅舅的错
He should've taken the legions south after Pompey.
他应该领兵南下
追击庞贝
The men know it, and it makes them restless.
他知道的，那就可以让他们不得安宁
当然了
Of course...
可他却装作是胸有成竹
he pretends it is a stratagem.
但是军营里连每只狗都知道
But every dog in camp
是赛维莉亚让他失去了男子气概
knows that Servilia has unmanned him.
他现在不会离开她了
He will not be parted from her.
我…
I...
你也看的出来
as you can tell,
依然勇猛如昔
am not unmanned.
简直是无法忍受
Intolerable. Intolerable!
无法忍受！
Calm yourself, Mother, please. You've become unbalanced.
冷静点，妈妈，你都快神经错乱了
为什么要管谁和他上床呢？
Why care so much who he beds? It is trivium.
这都是小事
How you take after your father- simple as milk.
你怎么跟你爸爸一样，单纯
要不是他在床上
If he were not mewling in bed with that witch he would be chasing down Pompey.
跟那个婊子缠绵，他早就追杀庞贝去了
这可不是小事，
It is not trivium. The Republic is at stake.
共和国现在很危险
Since when do you care about the Republic?
你什么时候开始关心共和国的？
我一直关心共和国
I care deeply about the Republic.
很不明智
It would be very unwise to cause trouble about this.
为了这个生事
当然了，
Of course. I wouldn't lower myself.
我不会自降身价的
这对肮脏的狗男女自然会被曝光的
Such sordid couplings have a way of turning out badly anyhow...
不需要任何人干什么
by no one's special doing.
家庭教师来了
Tutor has arrived.  Oh good.
哦，好
你的老师来了，在后院等呢
Your tutor has arrived and waits in the rear yard.
老师？什么老师？
Tutor? What tutor?
你早就该学学男人的技艺了
It's high time you learned the masculine arts.
如何格斗
How to fight and copulate and skin animals and so forth.
如何交媾，还有如何给动物剥皮
一切类似的东西
There's plenty of time yet for all that.
要学那些还有很长时间呢
你还有很多时间去看那些没用的书
Plenty of time for you to bury yourself in worthless scribbles.
你可以看这些希腊破书
You may read those old Greek fools
看到眼睛流血，但是你还是成不了智者
until blood runs from your eyes, you'll be none the wiser.
才不是呢，
I cannot agree. The Greek philosophers have much to teach us.
希腊的智者教会了我们很多东西
那么，这就是一个希腊智者
Well, here's a Greek philosopher for you.
我把你的那个士兵叫来了
I've engaged that soldier of yours.
乌瑞纳斯？
vorenus?  Was that it?
是他吗？
Not the sullen Catonian one, I don't like him.
不是那个一脸严肃的，
我不喜欢他
The cheerful brutish one.  Pullo.
是那个长得像野兽的
波罗，不错，就是他，
That's it. What extraordinary names these plebs have.
他们的名字真够怪的
波罗
Pullo.
防守！
Defend! Shield.
盾牌，盾牌
Shield.
别乱挥
Don't wave it about.
盾牌
Shield.
够了！！
Enough!
水
Water.
真是荒谬
This is absurd.
我没有搏击的天分
I have no soldiery stuff in me.
这么强行去打只会让我发烧
And this exertion brings on a fever.
我的脾脏都有感觉了
I feel it in my spleen.  You're just not used to it.
你只是没习惯罢了
It takes time. I've seen you kill.
这是需要时间的，
我见过你杀人
There's plenty of soldier in you.  It's not the killing.
你可是很有天分的
不是杀人的问题，
It's the waving about of swords I find tedious.
我只是觉得舞剑很没意思
我敢说我能够很容易地杀人
I dare say I can kill people readily enough,
只要他们不还手
as long as they're not fighting back.
别怕，小主人，
Never fear, young Dominus. We'll make a regular terror of you.
我们会把你变得让人胆寒
At best I will be a middling swordsman.
我只能成为庸手
It's better than nothing.  There you are wrong.
总比什么不会的强  那你就错了，
The graveyards are full of middling swordsmen.
死的都是那些庸手
与其当庸手还不如什么都不会好
Best to be no swordsman at all than a middling swordsman.
不准那样
Don't do that.
对不起
Excuse me.
小主人
Young Dominus...
我要请教一下你的意见
I need your advice on a delicate matter,
关于一件复杂的事情，如果你乐意的话，  没问题
if you'd be willing?  I am.
假设你看到了一件事情，让你怀疑另一件事情…
Suppose you saw something which made you suspect something--
一件可怕的事情
something terrible.
你会告诉被怀疑那个人的丈夫吗？
Would you tell the husband of the suspicious article?
怀疑她什么？
Suppose suspicion of what?
另一个男人
Another man.  Ah.
我猜你说的是乌瑞纳斯和他的妻子
We are speaking of vorenus and his wife, I presume.
我没有那么说过
I never said that.
在我看来光是怀疑还是不够的
It seems to me that suspicion alone is not enough to speak.
一旦怀疑到这种事情
Once spoken out, the suspicion of such depravity
找到实在的证据才是正确的
is real enough to do the work of truth.
要是你弄错了呢？
And what if you are mistaken?
那么乌瑞纳斯就会因为你的错误蒙羞
Then vorenus is dishonored by error.
事实最重要，没有事实你什么都不能说
Facts are necessary. Without facts, you must remain silent.
我知道你会说的那么透彻的
I knew you'd hit the jugular.
拒绝休战
Refuses truce.
现在怎么办？
What now?
怎么办？
多开心啊，嗯？
How happy, eh?
身为奴隶
To be a slave.
没有自己的意志
To have no will.
不用做任何决定
To make no decisions.
像段漂流的朽木
Driftwood.
那会是多么宁静的事啊
How very restful it must be.
伊拉斯提斯·富罗门  百夫长
Erastes Fulmen.  Centurion.
我来是想问一下你的建议
I have come to seek your counsel.
非常乐意
Always happy to help a friend.
我想问你借点钱
I need to borrow some money
听人说你有朋友从事贷款这个行业
and I am told you have friends in the lending trade.
不错
I do.
不错，我犹豫
I do. I only hesitate because I'm surprised.
是因为我有点惊讶
You was well found.
你手头应该不缺钱吧
My slaves were taken by the black flux.
我的奴隶都患了病
但是我一但有了资金我就会
But once I raise capital, I'll go up North and buy some more.
北上买更多奴隶
I have good contacts in Narbo.
我在纳尔波有很多关系
Be needing a big chunk then?  I will.
那就是要很大一笔了，对吧
不错
不行
I cannot.
把你引到这条路上来是不对的
Wrong to lead a citizen like yourself down that path.
这是个很粗暴的行业，放贷
Rough business, moneylending.
还不起钱就得受罪的
Man can't pay, he may have to suffer.
我要是把你介绍给放贷的
Was I to introduce you to a lender,
就像是把两头狼放到一个笼子里
I would be putting two wolves into one cage.
没有一方会得到好处
To neither's benefit.
不错，
You're right. You're right.
你是对的， 谢谢你抽时间
Thank you for your time.
百夫长，还有一条路可以赚钱
Centurion, there are other ways to make money.
像你这样的人，
Man like you, there's situations
只需要露个脸就可以值很多钱
his simple presence would be valuable.
像我这样的人？ 铁汉
A man like me.  A hard man.
恺撒第13军团的百夫长
First Spear Centurion in Caesar's mighty 13th.
我已经退役了  没关系
I'm no longer in the army.  No matter.
就你的样子已经足够了
Your bearing is enough.
你可以把你的荣耀和力量借给做生意的人
You would lend dignity and strength to business transactions.
如果你愿意的话，我就想雇用你
If you like, I could use you myself.
让你看看那些羡慕的眼光
Show you the onions.
谢谢你的好意，不过
That's good of you,
我还不清楚你要我作甚么？
but I still don't see what I would do exactly.
你来和我一起解决一些麻烦
You would come with me to discourage trouble.
没有人会跟百夫长找麻烦的
No one's going to mess with a First Spear Centurion.
做保镖？
I'd be a bodyguard.
会有很多钱
Good money.
我告诉过你的，我告诉过你的！
I told you! I told you!
对不起，我情不自禁，我没法…
I'm sorry, I couldn't help it. I can't--
去你的，
Damn you! Damn her! I am your wife.
我可是你的妻子！
Me. I am your wife.
我，你的妻子
莱蒂！
Lyde!
真好看
That's lovely.
看起来不像军人吧？
It's not too army-like?
像个做生意的
Like a man of deep business.
我不是生意人，只是个保镖
I'm no business man. I'm just a bodyguard.
刚开始嘛
It's a start.
赛维莉亚是恺撒的情妇
Please please, just for me.
大家都怎么了？
What is the matter with everybody?
恺撒的御用吹萧
Lock him up, girls! Lock him up!
Ohh! Oy, Calpurnia!
Ooh, yes!
恺撒是赛维莉亚的性奴
卡普尼娅…  不要管那些风言风语
Calpurnia-  Do not trouble yourself with denial.
我不是故意的  离开她，我不会再说了
I did not intend to.  Be rid of her and we'll say no more.
我们别…  否则就离婚
Let us not-  Or divorce will follow.
或许那不足以阻拦你
Perhaps that is not enough to deter you.
那就那样吧，反正我是不会关心的
Be that as it may, I am indifferent.
现在可不能离婚啊
We cannot divorce now.
她家族的支持很关键
Her family's influence will be critical--
我知道
I know it.
恺撒狂操赛维莉亚
Bring me out the smaller scales.
百夫长，你来的正好  公民
Centurion, you're right on time.  Citizen.
我们为什么不在市场上见面？
Why do we not meet in the Forum?
市场只是给那些快完成的交易，是公开的
Forum's only for closing deals, putting a hand on it public-like.
别吹了！
Enough of that Teuton droning!
要是你真想学那些无业游民那样吹口哨
If you want to whistle like someone's bum boy,
吹点好听的罗马小调
whistle a good Roman song at least.
她老是抱怨我像头大象
And she complained I was like an elephant.
塔基特，我的小鸭子
Tanjit, my honey duck,
你看起来很好嘛  伊拉特斯·富罗门
you're looking well.  Erastes Fulmen.
向你妈妈问好
I kiss your mother's feet.
请坐吧
Please, sit.
要什么东西吃喝？
Would you like something to eat, drink?
来点葡萄酒吧  我们没有酒，牛奶如何？
Wine will do.  We do not have wine. Milk, perhaps?
牛奶？你的尿喝完了吧？
Milk?! Run out of piss, did you?
真会开玩笑，呵呵
Humor. very good.
非得要我到这里来我觉得很不高兴，塔基特
I'm sad to have to come here, Tanjit.
非常不高兴
I'm very depressed.
我原以为我们都是生意人
I thought we were businessmen.
还以为我们可以互相理解，但是我们却
I thought we understood each other, yet here we are.
来到这种地步
Here we are.
我只会问你一次
I'm only going to ask once.
我的钱呢？
Where's my money?
我要买的猪呢？
Where's my truffle pigs?
你不就叫我订了50只猪嘛
50 pigs you have as ordered.
你给了我50只病猪
50 diseased and scrofulous pigs.
其中有一只知道怎么去找蘑菇吃的  狡猾的畜生
And one knows how to find truffles.  Tricky beasts.
他们没吃橡树果吗？
Haven't been eating acorns, have they?
去他妈的蘑菇，太多的橡树果了
Fucks them for truffling, too much acorns.
我可以还你1/4的钱，出于我们的友谊
I will give you one quarter price. Out of friendship.
你一个子儿都别想少，你这个胡子拉扎的奸贼
You'll give me every mumping denarius
真的
you cac-faced cunny!  Really,
让我们不要用野蛮来解决问题
there is no call for rudeness.
我听说印度人死了以后生命不灭？真的吗？
I'm told Hindus live on after death. Is that true?
我们死了也会腐化，跟你们一样
Our bodies die and decay as yours will.
但是我们的灵魂永生
But our souls live on eternally.
嗯，那样的安排不错
Well, that's nice arrangements.
那么你就是不怕死咯？ 一点都不怕
You're not afraid to die then?  Not at all.
敲断他的手
Break his arm.
还我钱，你这个猴崽子
Give me my money, you monkey's cunt.
去死吧
Kiss my ass.
割了他的喉咙
Cut his throat.
快割！
Cut it!
你在干什么？
What are you doing?
发生什么事了？
What happened?
怎么了？告诉我
What's wrong? Tell me.
伊拉特斯·富罗门要我杀人
Erastes Fulmen asked me to kill a man.
你不答应？
You refused him?
我还能怎么样？
What else was I to do?
我又不是强盗  你当然不是了
I am no bandit.  Of course you're not.
你不能像从前那样杀人了
You couldn't do other than you did.
不过我们怎么给租金啊？
But how are we to pay the rent?
怎么养活孩子们？
How are we to feed the children?
他来了！
He's here!
我真高兴！我还以为你不会…
I'm so glad! I thought you might not--
抱歉我不能呆下去了
I regret I cannot stay.
我是来道别的
I've come to say goodbye.
道别？
Goodbye?
我要南下追击庞贝
I'm going south in pursuit of Pompey,
我们不会再见面了
and we shall not see each other again.
什么？永不？ 永不
What, never?  Never.
别这么开玩笑
Don't joke so.
我没有开玩笑
I am not joking.
是不是因为那些愚蠢的画
Is this because of some foolish graffi--
赛维莉亚，我们结束了
Servilia, we are done.
你怎么能这么说？
How can you say that?
我们彼此爱着对方
We love each other.
是的
Be assured,
并不是我不爱你
it is not that l do not love you.
我这么做是与我的意愿相背的
I do this against my own inclination.
不过，有更危急的事情要我去处理
There are, however, larger issues at stake,
而我必须做出对共和国有利的事
and I must do what is right for the Republic.
共和国？！
The Republic?!
为什么这么高兴？妈妈？
Why so happy, Mother?
没事
No reason.
一点事情都没有？
None at all?
没有什么聪明的计划得逞了？
No clever little plan bearing fruit?
没有，我的宝贝
None at all, my poppet.
没有其他的暗示
Nor should you suggest otherwise...
对任何人
to anyone.
这么慌慌张张的干什么？
What's all the fuss?
我们明天南下  太好了
We go south tomorrow.  Excellent.
要是我们动作快的话，不到初一庞贝就会遭殃了
If we move fast, Pompey will be eating dust by the Kalends.
你和第13军团留在这里，维持秩序
You'll remain here with the 13th to keep the peace.
维持秩序？
Keep the peace?
罗马城由你来接管。我会把波斯卡留下来帮你
The city will be in your charge. I'll leave Posca to assist you.
太荒谬了，我是军人，又不是维持秩序的
That's ridiculous! I'm a soldier, not a peacekeeper.
你要服从命令，妈的
You will follow orders, damn you.
我在考虑…
I was considering...
I'm sick and tired--
我在附近有个农庄
...I have a farm near here.
一年里这个时候景色漂亮极了
Lovely at this time of year.
我想我可能去那里
I was considering that I might go there.
呆在那里过收获期
Stay for the harvest.
要么你和我一起去？
Perhaps you'd like to join me?
谢谢了
That is very kind,
不过我还是留在这里
but I think I will stay here.
留下来没有好处的
No good will come of staying.
不知道
I don't know.
至少大海让人觉得鼓舞
The sea air is bracing at least.
你若是不走，我也走不了
If you do not go then I cannot go, I suppose.
那样我就显得太懦夫了
It would look cowardly.
有关系吗？即使不是如此你也早就知道了
What matter? You would know it were not so.
是啊，我当然早就知道
Oh, I would know, certainly.
但是我不像你
But I do not have
有一个光芒显赫的姓氏
a grand shining old name like you.
我得把我的族姓好好保留下去
I must keep my name well-polished,
否则就会永远抬不起头来
else it looks very dull.
那我就得留下来了  对不起了，老家伙
I must stay then  I'm sorry, old man.
士兵！
Soldier!
你在当值
You're on duty.
将军可以见你了
The general will see you now.
把这份抄录了
Copy this.
公民，你想干什么？
What do you want, citizen?
我重新考虑了我的情况，长官
I've reconsidered my position, sir.
我想接受你的提议
I wish to accept your offer.
我的提议？
My offer?
成为留用士官
Of entry into Evocati.
要是条件都没有过时的话
If same terms still apply.
我说过你可以当留用士官吗？
I said you could join Evocati?
是的，长官，你说过
With respect, sir, you did.
我开出什么条件？
What terms did I offer?
一级留用士官，1万赛斯特斯
Evocati Prefect first grade, 10,000 sesterces.
那个条件真够慷慨的，不过你却拒绝了
That's a generous offer. One which you declined.
一般我从不会两次给出同一个提议
Normally, I would never make the same offer twice,
不过你很走运
but you're lucky.
恺撒走了
Cesar is away,
我只有一个人
and I am here alone.
我会很需要能人
And I shall need good men.
所以我给你
So I give it you,
升到士官
promotion to Prefect
9千赛斯特斯
and 9,000 sesterces.
谢谢你，长官
Thank you, sir.
为了回报我的慷慨
In return for my generosity,
卢休斯·乌瑞纳斯
Lucius vorenus,
我要你的忠诚
I expect loyalty.
至死的忠诚
Loyalty unto death.
Unto death, sir.
欢迎回来
Welcome home.
解散
Dismissed.
带他进来，主人
Put him here. Domina...
他是其中一个，画那些淫画的人
this is one of them that drew the filthy pictures.
让他开口没花多长时间
Didn't take long to make him speak.
嗯？你这个禽兽！
Eh? Creature!
谁雇他的？
Who hired him?
蒂门，那个犹太人
Timon, the Horse Jew.
阿提娅的人
Atia's man.
给我穿衣服
Dress me.
搞定了  他们让你回去了？
It's done.  They'll have you back?
是的
They will.
一级留用士官，9千赛斯特斯
Evocati Prefect first grade, 9,000 sesterces.
我把自己卖给了暴君
I've sold myself to a tyrant.
只能这样了
It had to be done.
谢谢你
Thank you.
朱利埃的众神
Gods of the Junii,
以此祭品我请求您召集
with this offering I ask you to summon
堤喀，美格拉和复仇女神
Tyche, Maegara and Nemesis,
让他们见证这个诅咒
so that they witness this curse.
以我先人灵魂的名义
By the spirits of my ancestors,
我诅咒盖乌斯·朱利叶斯·恺撒
I curse Gaius Julius Caesar.
让他的阳具枯萎
Let his penis wither.
让他的骨头折断
Let his bones crack.
让他看到自己的军团被鲜血淹没
Let him see his legions drown in their own blood.
地狱的众神
Gods of the inferno,
我向您供上他的四肢
I offer to you his limbs,
他的头颅
his head,
他的嘴
his mouth,
他的呼吸
his breath,
他的话语
his speech,
他的双手
his hands,
他的肝脏
his liver,
他的心脏还有胃
his heart, his stomach.
地狱的众神，请让我看到他饱受痛苦
Gods of the inferno, Iet me see him suffer deeply
我将欣喜地
and I will rejoice
把自己奉献给您
and sacrifice to you.
以我先人灵魂的名义
By the spirits of my ancestors,
我诅咒阿提娅
I curse Atia of the Julii.
让她被野狗强暴
Let dogs rape her.
让他的儿女死去
Let her children die
让她的家园被焚毁
and her houses burn.
让她怀着痛苦羞耻度过漫长的一生
Let her live a long life of bitter misery and shame.
地狱的众神
Gods of the inferno,
我将供上她的四肢
I offer to you her limbs,
她的头颅
her head,
她的嘴，她的呼吸
her mouth, her breath,
她的话语，她的心脏
her speech, her heart,
她的肝脏，她的胃
her liver, her stomach.
地狱的众神
Gods of the inferno,
让我看到她备受痛苦
Iet me see her suffer deeply,
我将会欣喜地
and I will rejoice
把自己奉献给您
and sacrifice to you.
好了，我的朋友  你们想干什么？
Here we are then, friend.  What do you want?
告诉我们你和尼奥比之间发生了什么事情
Tell us what's between you and Niobe.  Eh?
尼奥比？没有，从来没有
Niobe? Nothing. Never.
我向朱庇特神起誓，绝对没有！
I swear by Jupiter, never!
若是我撒谎，让复仇女神把我的眼睛挖出来！
Furies tear my eyes out if I lie!
我见到你们在一起的时候在干什么？
What were you doing when I saw you with her?
我和我妻子吵架了
My wife- we were fighting.
我去问问尼奥比应该怎么办，仅此而已
I went to Niobe for advice, that's all.
我哭了，要是你非得知道真相的话
I was crying, if you want to know the truth,
尼奥比很同情我
and Niobe commiserated with me.
我决不…决不会…
I would never- I would never--
可能他说的是真的  撒谎
Maybe he's telling the truth.  Lying.
没有！没有撒谎！    撒谎！
I'm not!  I'm not!   Lying.
如果他说你是撒谎，我信他
If he says you're lying, then I believe him.
这个小孩子比你想象的还要聪明
This boy is clever like you don't know what.
不，不要，求你了  别吵！
No, please, I beg you!  Hush.
不要让自己难堪
Don't embarrass yourself.
我们知道你撒谎，知道的，懂吗？
We know you're lying. We know it, you understand?
我们得杀了你
We have to kill you.
我从来没有碰过她  伊万达，往前一点
I never touched her.  Evander, move forward.
你的小命快没了
Your life is over. The only question is,
唯一的问题是，你想怎么个死法？
how do you want to die?
我们要知道真相
We need to hear the truth.
要是你坚持不说真话，我们会折磨你
If you persist in lying to us, we'll torture you.
你再备受几小时的痛苦煎熬和恐怖之后才会慢慢死去
You'll die only after many hours of agony and horror.
不过要是老老实实，你会死的很快，毫无痛苦
But give us honesty now, and you'll go swiftly, painlessly.
求你们了  伊万达，说真话
Please.  Evander, tell the truth.
折磨他  说的好听，真有你的
Torture him.  Juno's cunt, but you're salty.
我开始还还怕把你带来呢
And I was worried about bringing you.
那就开始吧
Go on then.
其实我没有折磨过人
I've never actually tortured anyone.
不知道该怎么折磨  不知道？
I don't know how.  You don't know how?
他们都有专家的  割了他的拇指
They have specialists!  Why not cut off his thumbs?
很好的开始
That's good enough. It's a start.
尼奥比和我是情人，我招了
Niobe and I were lovers. I confess it.
杀了我吧
Kill me if you must.
等等
Hold.
还有呢？
What else?
没有了，杀了我吧
Nothing else. Kill me.
你又撒谎！
You're lying again.
站在你面前的是波罗
You stand at Pluto's door. Will you sully his threshold with lies?
你想用谎言挑战他忍耐的极限吗？
I am done talking.  Cut off his thumbs.
我说完了  再割一个拇指
那个孩子！
The child!
孩子是我的  孩子？什么孩子？
The child is mine!  Child? What child?
卢休斯
Lucius.
那个婴儿
The baby.
快杀了我吧
Please, kill me now. Please.
卢休斯，沃里娜的儿子？ 尼奥比的儿子
Lucius, vorenus' son?  Niobe's son.
我的儿子
My son.
是我的
It's mine.
我们已经把这个禽兽给埋了
We have buried this evil now.
以后你再也不许提起这件事
You must never speak of it again.
千万不能让乌瑞纳斯知道
vorenus must never know.
决不可以
Never.
战神啊
Father Mars Strider,
这个人已经忠诚地为你守夜
this man has done faithful vigil for you.
我们请求您赐他予庇护
We therefore ask you to take him under your protection.
让他的敌人望风而逃
May his enemies flee from him.
让敌人的城墙颤抖
May their city walls crumble.
让他们的牧群和女人为我们捕获
May their cattle and women be taken.
这个人…
This man...
现在是留用士官了
is now Evocati.
大人，他们坐船去希腊了
Sir, they've sailed for Greece.
翻译:TLF字幕组